<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons against agreement with a late printed paper, intituled Foundations of freedome, or, The agreement of the people whereby it doth appear that the particulars proposed in the said paper are not foundations of freedom but of tyranny and slavery to the people, being destructive to religion, laws, liberty, and government against our Covenant and Protestantism, and very dangerous and unsafe for the kingdome / by William Ashhurst.</title>
            <author>Ashhurst, William, 1617-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26020</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3978</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26663</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09523280</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09523280</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43435</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26020)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43435)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1323:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons against agreement with a late printed paper, intituled Foundations of freedome, or, The agreement of the people whereby it doth appear that the particulars proposed in the said paper are not foundations of freedom but of tyranny and slavery to the people, being destructive to religion, laws, liberty, and government against our Covenant and Protestantism, and very dangerous and unsafe for the kingdome / by William Ashhurst.</title>
                  <author>Ashhurst, William, 1617-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Reprinted at the charge of Sir Francis Nethersole Kinght [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Originally printed for Thomas Underhill in 1648.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Foundations of freedom.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43435:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43435:1"/>
            <p>REASONS AGAINST AGREEMENT With a late Printed Paper, intituled
<hi>Foundations of Freedome:</hi> Or the AGREEMENT Of the PEOPLE. Whereby it doth appear, that the Particulars propoſed in the ſaid Paper are not
<hi>Foundations of Freedom,</hi> but of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and ſlavery</hi> to the People; being deſtructive to <hi>Religion, Laws, Liberty,</hi> and
<hi>Government;</hi> againſt our <hi>Covenant</hi> and
<hi>Proteſtations,</hi> and very dangerous and unſafe for the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM ASHHURST</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill,</hi> 1648. And now reprinted in the Year of our Lord, 1659. At the charge of Sir
<hi>Francis Netherſole</hi> Kinght; and by him humbly recommended to the ſerious conſideration of all, and every Member of the preſent Houſe of Commons; and of all other wiſe and true hearted Engliſh-men: As no leſs conſiderable at this time then at that when they were publiſhed by the Author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43435:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have no more to ſay to the Reader, but that when I had conſidered the Printed Paper, intituled, <hi>Foundations of Freedom, or an Agreement of the People;</hi> I was very much unſatisfied with it, and ſo were others I met with. And finding that the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces upon it would fall out amongſt thoſe who are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to friendſhip and agreement, both for the good of the Kingdom and their own good, I thought it unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and unſafe, to let ſo great diſ-ſatisfactions lie pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately heating together, until they might kindle into an hotter flame of diſcontent, eſpecially it having ever been (as it is ſtill) my opinion (which I have not hid) that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in this caſe ſhould be ended by Reaſon, not by Oppoſition: And ſeeing the Publiſher of the Paper calls upon every man for his Reaſons againſt it, I have here brought him mine under my hand, wherein although I am ſenſible that I may diſcover my own weakneſs and folly, yet I ever hating all private Contrivances, or to do any thing of publick Concernment in a Corner, have judged it more honeſt (and that ſhall ever go for wiſdom with me) to uſe plain dealing, which if it be (according to the Proverb) a jewell, I am ſure, was never more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious then at this time.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43435:2"/>
            <head>REASONS AGAINST <hi>Agreement,</hi> with a late Printed Paper, Intituled, <hi>An Agreement of the People.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Publiſher of this Paper called, <hi>An Agreement of the People,</hi> tells us, that it was tendred to the Conſideration of the General, and Councel of the Army; but before it was Approved by them (which I hope it never will) he held it juſt to be publiſhed, that men might offer their Reaſons Againſt it: wherein he is ſo ingenuous; that however both the Epiſtle and Paper might give occaſion to ſome perſonal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, yet I will only give him fairly my reaſons why I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Agree to his Paper; having for the more clear proceeding firſt laid down the moſt principal parts of this Agreement, which (as I take it) is briefly, <hi>That the people who ſhall ſubſcribe this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> ſhall Agree, To take away this Parliament, and to chuſe an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Repreſentative
<hi>conſiſting of</hi> 300. <hi>men,</hi> who ſhall have full power without the conſent <hi>or concurrence of any other perſon or perſons (either King or Houſe of Peers)</hi> to make, repeal, alter, and declare Laws: <hi>and that none do reſiſt their Laws or Orders upon pain of death, except ſuch Repreſentatives expreſly violate this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and they ſhall have power</hi> to chooſe a Councel of State for the managing of publick affairs: But that they ſhall not have power to continue in force, or make any Laws, Oaths, and Covenants, whereby to compel by penalties, or otherwiſe any perſon to any thing in or about matters of Faith, Religion,
<pb facs="tcp:43435:3"/>or Gods worſhip, or to reſtrain any perſon from the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Faith, or exerciſe of Religion, according to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in any houſe or place, except ſuch as are or ſhall be ſet apart for the publick worſhip, <hi>nevertheleſs the inſtruction or dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the Nation in a publick way for the matters of faith, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or diſcipline, ſo it be not compulſive, or expreſs Popery, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to their diſcretion:</hi> with like reſtriction in other matters of leſs conſequence.</p>
            <p>I am very much unſatisfied with this Paper, both for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and matter of it, for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe it propoſeth, that the people (or rather ſome ſmall part of them) without any colour of Law or Right, ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together to alter the preſent Government,</hi> and to take away a legal right from Burroughs to chooſe Members to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; which admitted, they may with as much Juſtice and Right agree to take away any Law, or any mans life or eſtate, by which Rule we could enjoy nothing but at the will of any number of men that would call themſelves The People. <hi>And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ground that thoſe who ſhall ſubſcribe</hi> this Agreement <hi>may call themſelves the People, might thoſe who ſhall refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it, and thoſe who are not admitted to ſubſcribe it, both call themſelves the People, and at any time hereafter pretend like right to do the ſame, or like things; which muſt lay a foundation of certain confuſions.</hi> Neither can there be aſſurance of any ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement whatſoever in this way, for what thoſe who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the People Agree upon now, they may alter within a month, or ſooner if they pleaſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe if there were a right by this way to alter the Government (as there is not) yet it is not reaſonable to attempt ſo great a matter, the Conſequences whereof must be of ſo vaſt concernment to the Kingdome before the inconveniences of the preſent Government have been plainly diſcovered, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly debated: And being found out, tryall had been made whether by the preſent unqueſtionable power there might not have been found a remedy either by ſome Additions, or ſmaller A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tions, without putting things to ſo great an hazard as an
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tion in the Supreame Power<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43435:3"/>muſt bring, and that without offering any reaſon for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is there only theſe general reaſons againſt the whole Paper, but if the ſubject matter of it, and the proceedings inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereupon were lawful, yet there are many Reaſons againſt the particulars in it, which I ſhall proceed with.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe it doth propoſe to take away (not only this King) but all Kings, and the Houſe of Peers out of the Supreame Judicatory of this Kingdome, and that for ever, without ſhewing any neceſſity of it;</hi> which the Papiſts, Delinquents, and ill-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected perſons amongſt us (well perceiving how great a diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction it would bring) did frequently charge upon <hi>this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> as their deſign, whereupon to vindicate themſelves from ſuch aſpertions, they <hi>have made and publiſhed ſeveral Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that they would not alter the Government of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by King, Lords and Commons;</hi> And this Kingdome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had ſo many hundred years experience of this preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, in the moſt part of which time they having lived in peace and plenty; and when any wars have heretofore happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between the King and the People, no ſuch alterations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ever deſired or attempted. It is not imaginable that they will now deſire to change it for they know not what, for ſo are all alterations of Government untill the conveniencies or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies be found out by experience. All I will further adde upon this Reaſon is, that this poor waſted Kingdome doth not ſtand in need of ſo great a diviſion and diſtraction in the courſe of all proceedings at home, and to incurre ſuch dangers from abroad, as would in reaſon be the Conſequences of this Alteration.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe this Paper propoſeth the abſolute taking away of the power and priviledges of the Parliaments of</hi> England, <hi>which we are bound to preſerve and maintain, not only as Engliſhmen, but as Chriſtians;</hi> moſt part of the Kingdom having ſolemnly ſworn it to the moſt high God, and one to another in the Vow and Proteſtation of the 5. of <hi>May</hi> 1641. wherein we further vow and proteſt, to oppoſe, and by all good wayes and means endeavour to bring unto condigne puniſhment all ſuch as ſhall either by force, Practice, or Councels, Plots, Conſpiracies, or<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43435:4"/>otherwiſe do any thing to the contrary. And likewiſe in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant of 27. of
<hi>September,</hi> 1643. not only we in this Kingdom, but the moſt part of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> have ſworn to preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of the Parliaments in both Kingdomes. Now <hi>the Paper doth not only propoſe, to take away the Rights and Priviledges, but the</hi> Parliaments <hi>of</hi> England <hi>themſelves, as they were conſtituted when theſe Oaths were taken, to which the words according to the lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſenſe of them (which is the rule of Oaths) muſt relate,</hi> for we could not ſwear to that which was not, or to ſomething that was only like a Parliament therefore no man (as I conceive) who hath taken either the vow and Proteſtation, or the Solemn League and Covenant, can agree to this agreement, unleſs he dare make himſelf guilty of moſt palpable and notorious Perjury.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe it propoſeth the taking away this unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Legal Parliament only by a forceable agreement, without any Authority;</hi> And in the room of it to ſettle a repreſentative which hath not ſo much as a colour of Legal right: by which means, <hi>Although force and Power may hinder this Parliament, from acting, yet the being of it cannot be taken away, but by the like Law that made it. So as we ſhall have a Repreſentative that will pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to a Legiſlative power, and a Parliament who ought to have it both in being at once, which may lead the Kingdom into miſerable uncertainties and diſtractions, when any number that will make an Houſe of Commons, and any num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that will make an Houſe of Peers aſſembled in any place within</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>will have more power to make and repeale Laws then theſe Repreſentatives, Although all were done that the Paper deſires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Reaſ. Becauſe there is ſuch a desperate encroachment upon the Liberties of the people of</hi> England, propoſed in the Election of this Repreſentative; it being a known Maxime in Law, that no power could lawfully impoſe upon the Liberties or proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the people of this Kingdome, but either by their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Conſent, or general Aſſent in Parliament where every man is repreſented. But by this Paper, as well all thoſe who have been moſt faithful to the Parliament and Kingdome, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43435:4"/>their lives and eſtates in this cauſe (if in Conſcience they cannot ſubſcribe this Agreement) as the Delinquents and Papiſts that are moſt of all obnoxious to the Law, ſhall be debarred from Electing or being elected, yet they ſhall have Laws and taxes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon them, &amp; by them who for number are the leaſt party in the Kingdom, and by thoſe to whom they give no conſent nor truſt, which is as perfect ſlavery, as any Tyrant could impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe the declaring of Agreement with this Paper by Subſcription, will not only be a means more to draw, but alſo to keep thoſe who have adhered to the Parliament in this cauſe in parties, factions and diviſions:</hi> For after they are once all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by Subſcribers, or non-ſubſcribers, it will make them more ſtrange one to another, and to with-draw that affection and confidence from each other that is neceſſary for them as Chriſtians, and as wiſe men; who ſhould rather ſtudy how to finde out ways of Union for their mutual preſervation againſt the common Enemy, then take this courſe which I feare may prove a way of great danger to us, <hi>becauſe it will encreaſe jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies</hi> in thoſe who muſt be non-ſubſcribers, <hi>that though they are now only minde uncapable of publick truſt and employment, yet they are not ſecure, but they may be proceeded againſt further afterwards by the new Repreſentative unto high (if not the higheſt) puniſhments:</hi> which doubts and feares will encreaſe if the Supream power be wholly put into the hand of a party who differ from them in principles of Religion and civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and they have no viſible ſecurity before-hand to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy Religion and their Liberties; the want of ſecuring whereof, as it made many of them refuſe to agree with the King, ſo will it binde them from agreement with any power on Earth; <hi>upon which ground it is to be feared they cannot but look upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as under oppreſſion, both in their Liberties, properties, and Conſciences:</hi> wherein I ſpeak the more freely, that every man might labour and endeavour to prevent ſuch breaches, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially amongſt thoſe which feare God, and that none of them might adhere to this Paper, wherein it is eſpecially to be noted, that all the diſtractions, diviſions, evils and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43435:5"/>that ſhall happen upon either ſubſcribing or not ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, is only to thoſe who have been united in this cauſe, the common enemy being thereby ſtrengthned, united, and kept from the teſt of this ſubſcription.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe this will tend to the utter ſubverting and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away Magiſtracy and Government out of the Kingdome, not only by placing ſuch a ſupream power (under whom all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate do act) as at least will be diſputed;</hi> And thereby that diſtance and reverence that God hath put upon his Ordinance of Magiſtracy being removed, it is like to fall into contempt; <hi>But by this Paper</hi> the Laws and Orders of this Repreſentative ſhall not bind, or be of any force even to thoſe who agree and ſubſcribe to the Paper. For although it ſeems to put the penalty of death upon the reſiſters of their Orders, yet there is one little exception that makes it lawful for all men (eſpecially that have power) to reſiſt and diſobey them, the words are theſe: <hi>Except ſuch Repreſentative ſhall expreſly violate this Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> which leaves every man to be a Judge of it, there being by this Paper no other power intended to be above this Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative to judge it; Nor doth it appoint either how, or by whom, this judgement all be made: Therefore <hi>every man that will but ſay they have broken this Agreement, and hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to make it good, ſhall not offend, but juſtifie his diſobedience,</hi> oppoſing of their Laws or Orders by force. And where there is this principle that Judgement is out of the legal Judges, there can be no Magiſtracy, Authority, or Government. <hi>It is true, that (there being no perfection in any thing here below) all Judges and Supream Authorities may erre, and do evil, but if upon that ground any multitudes ſhould be their Judges, is not the reaſon as good and much more ſtrong, that thoſe multitudes (who cannot be judged) may erre, and do evil, by how much they are acted by fancy, and as they are poſſeſſed by others,</hi> And according to their ſudden and preſent Apprehenſions, rather then by principles, Reaſon, or Judgement; neither are they bound by thoſe conſiderable intereſts to ſeek the good and tranquillity of the Kingdome, that uſually thoſe have who are called to be Judges; and eſpecially they are not ſo obliged<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43435:5"/>in duty to God, becauſe the Magiſtrates are called by God to be Judges, therefore they muſt judge righteouſly, as they will anſwer it to him upon higheſt penalty, <hi>The loſſe of their ſouls.</hi> I might further ſhew, that by the Moral Law, the Law of nature, and the poſitive Laws of God, Judgement doth wholly reſt in the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. But this point being only for the more abundant clearing, yet not of abſolute neceſſity to this Reaſon, I will inſiſt no further upon it, there being enough to demonſtrate, that if no man ought to be puniſht for oppoſing any Law or Order of this Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>if they break this Agreement,</hi> and that every man may be his own Judg whether they have broken this Agreement or no; then although there may be a color, yet there is really no Authority in this Repreſentative. And if not in this, which is to be made the Supream, then much leſs have any inferior Judicatories that ſhall act under them; and ſo that great Ordinance of God, Magiſtracy, whereby he preſerves humane ſociety, ſhall be taken out of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe this Paper allows a tolleration of</hi> Popery, only with a reſtriction to the Magiſtrate, that he ſhall not inſtruct or direct it publickly; But both he, and all the people that will, may profeſs, and practiſe it in their houſes, which is a large ſtep to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the publick profeſſion of it; eſpecially ſeeing that by gaining thus much, this juſt plea will lie for the freedome of it: That <hi>there is no reaſon to except Popery, when thoſe that are</hi> guilty of Atheiſme, the deniers of God, or any Perſon in the Trinity, The greateſt blaſphemers, and curſers of God, with thoſe <hi>that profeſs any hereſie or errour have their liberty,</hi> and are not excepted, and therefore by theſe principles (in Juſtice) Popery muſt likewiſe go out free, although it may be judged no policity to ſpeak it out at this time. When I conſider this, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the other parts of this Paper, which onely tends to divide thoſe who have adhered to the Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in this cauſe, and ſee what care is taken (to the end we might be the better deſtroyed) that nothing be propoſed which might divide the common Enemy amongſt themſelves, but they muſt remain intire, and united (which I did intend for a diſtinct Reaſon againſt the Paper.) <hi>This is a plain diſcovery to</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43435:6"/>me, <hi>that the whole was made and contrived by ſome Jeſuite,</hi> with the advice of ſome of the Kings old Counſellors, although it is poſſible that ſome honeſt men may be couſened into the acting of it for them. But to returne to the point,
<hi>Here we have a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that hath neither compluſive nor reſtrictive power in matters of Religion, but both he and the people are freely left to be of any Religion that they pleaſe, or of no Religion if they pleaſe;</hi> yet the Magiſtrate (if it ſtand with his diſcretion) ſhall have a To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration to inſtruct and direct in a publike way (all that will be inſtructed and directed by him (for all are left to their liberty) in matters of Faith, Worſhip, or Diſcipline, whereby he is at liberty to inſtruct according to truth, or in any error, <hi>ſo that for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it be not Popery, yet in truth the beſt contrivance to build up Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; at laſt upon the ruines of Religion by Atheiſm and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> which the more it is conſidered, the more it will be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by all honeſt and godly men in the Kingdome. If I had more patience I might ſay much more upon this Reaſon, but I think this is enough.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe it will leave</hi> Ireland <hi>to the Rebels:</hi> and the Proteſtant party and Forces there, to miſery and ruine: not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by our diſtractions, but becauſe the managing of the Warre of <hi>Ireland</hi> is in this Parliament, wherein the new Repreſentative will have no Authority.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe it tends to divide us from</hi> Scotland; the particulars held forth in this Agreement being directly contrary to the declared principles both of that State and Church, and deſtructive to all the faithful in that Kingdome both Miniſters and people, that have adhered to us in this Cauſe.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe it deſtroys the cauſe for which we have fought,</hi> wherein ſo many Noble and Gallant Gentlemen, and others, have not only hazarded, but loſt their lives. The quarrel firſt beginning upon the Kings impoſing on the Power and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, and interrupting their proceedings. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe that joyned with the King in this Warre (although it was ſo foul an act deſtructive to the Liberties of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that they profeſſed the contrary, yet it was apparent that they) did fight to deſtroy this Parliament; Therefore
<hi>to joyn<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43435:6"/>with others to take away this Parliament by a forcible agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is to do the enemies work, and give them the Cauſe. And is againſt the great Truſt which hath been, and is given by the Parliament to all the Souldiers that have had, or have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions from then, wherein they are ſpecially intrusted to fight for</hi> The preſervation of this Parliament. <hi>And when all Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers do well conſider, that without the Authority of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their Taking up Armes were Treaſon, and their killing of men were murther;</hi> and that it is the Authority by which they have endemnity &amp; preſent pay, and ſecurity for their Arrears, and that as the change of Authority would make many queſtions in other things, ſo would it do in theſe. It being alſo evident, that as the Parliament cannot well be without their forces, ſo they cannot be without the Parliaments Authority. Upon all theſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, the Souldiers have reaſon to be againſt this Paper, which propoſeth by agreement to take away the Cauſe they have fought for.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Reaſ. <hi>Becauſe although there were a quiet poſſeſſion of all that is deſired in this Paper, yet it were not like to stand long, the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of all that are most conſiderable, obliging them to be against the keeping of this Agreement.</hi> For inſtance, <hi>In reaſon all Kings will be againſt it,</hi> for they, and their Heirs, and Succeſſors are utterly excl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ded out of this Government. <hi>The Peers will be againſt it,</hi> there being likewiſe an excluſion of the Houſe of Peers. <hi>The ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers will be againſt it,</hi> becauſe it offers forcibly to take away the Parliament they have fought for, whoſe Authority gave them a being as Souldiers, and under whoſe Authority they act. <hi>The Magiſtrates or people of that quality capable of government will be againſt it,</hi> becauſe it leaves at the beſt but the colour of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, with no power but ſuch as is alterable, and revokeable at the pleaſure of any multitude. <hi>The faithful and conſcientious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters will be againſt it,</hi> for as it gives them no protection, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, encouragement, or aſſiſtance by the Magiſtrate; ſo it leaves all their people to the practice and profeſſion of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Atheiſm, Hereſie, Errour and Prophaneneſs without controll. <hi>And it is like that moſt of the Religious and diſcreet people will be against it,</hi> becauſe it neither provides for increaſe of<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43435:7"/>piety, nor give ſecurity for the enjoyment of Liberty or Property, nor hopes of Union, which might bring a ſettlement and peace. <hi>And what ſorts of people are left whoſe intereſt it would be to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this Agreement, I leave any one to conſider, whether they will not be only ſuch, who becauſe they cannot bring themſelves within the protection of the Laws eſtabliſht and preſent Government, will poſſibly ſign this Agreement, that ſo they may bring the Law and Government to their wills and corupt intereſts;</hi> for ſo indeed they do that ſubſcribe this Agreement. No obedience being to be given to this Repreſentative but in their keepinging this agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and there being no other Judges thereof but the Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, who in the reſult of all have the Law in their own wills: Upon all which grounds there is no hope that this Agreement if it were made (as is deſired) would either preſerve it ſelf, or that any who were moſt conſiderable, could be obliged to keep it, ſo as nothing could be expected from it but to be a foundation for new confuſion.</p>
            <p>I will cloſe theſe Reaſons with this profeſſion, That I am far from arguing that this Parliament ſhould not (in this manner) be taken away out of any baſe or low end, that I might ſtill continue a Member of it, for I dare &amp; do appeal to God, who is the ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of all hearts, that I know no outward thing to befall me, that I ſhould account my ſelf more happy in, then to be legally diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from that Service. But in this way to tear up the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all Government, and to rear up ſo miſerable a thing in the room, It behoves every true-hearted Engliſhman that ſees it to be ſenſible, not for his own, but for the Kingdoms ſake: and that really ſet me on work at this time.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now onely adde ſome ſhort general obſervations upon ſeveral particulars I finde at the end of this Paper prepared al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready for this new Repreſentative; wherein are deſires to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>That no mans life be taken away but for Murther. That no man be Impriſoned for Debt: That no Tythes be paid: That there be no reſtriction
<hi>(which is no regulation)</hi> of Trade. That there be no Lawyers, nor Law, but new Rules in Engliſh, to be made by the new Repreſentative; And twelve men in every<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43435:7"/>Hundred to be Judges of all cauſes, who are likewiſe intended to ſupply the Offices of all Mayors, Sheriffs, Juſtices of Peace, Deputies, &amp;c. Theſe are the deſires of them who labour for a new Repreſentative inſtead of Parliaments. And it ſeems they hope to chooſe ſuch a Repreſentative as will grant them all. Indeed if theſe muſt be had, I agree there is a neceſſity (by ſome means or other) to take away this Parliament; for I believe that they would never grant ſuch things, as the making of Laws in the favour of Treaſons, Burglaries, Felonies, Sodomy, Buggery, Rapes, and ſuch like abominations, from which the puniſhments of death is (by theſe men) deſired to be taken off, eſpecially conſidering that the many good Lawes which have been made under higheſt penalties (as now they ſtand) no not hinder nor deter men from thoſe foule offences which are daily and frequently committed in all parts of the Kingdome; and therefore there rather appears need of ſtricter proviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p>But when the new Repreſentative ſhall take theſe things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſideration, they may finde that there will be no need to take away any penalties from a Malefactor, by a Law to keep them from Juſtice, if they do but grant the hundred Courts as is deſired (who can but ſit ſeldome) and thereupon all Mayors, Sheriffs, Juſtices of Peace, &amp;c. who are Officers ever ready, and by whoſe Authority the Malefactors are apprehended, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, committed, and brought to Juſtice; being taken away, the Offendors are like to go free without any ſuch Law. Eſpecially when theſe Hundred Courts act the parts not onely of all the Lawyers, but of all the Judges in the Kingdom; And all this Juſtice to be done, and lie in the breſts of twelve men in every Hundred, who may be choſen of men that can neither write, reade, nor have any eſtates reſponſable, if they ſhould be found guilty of Bribery, or any other high miſdemeanours: by this means we are like to have Juſtice at all adventure, be it right or wrong. If I ſhould go over the reſt of the afore-mentioned par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, I ſhould not keep my word, for there is ſo much to be ſaid againſt every of them, that I could not be ſhort, nor is it very neceſſary to be done: for in the bare reading of them it<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43435:8"/>doth too much appear, that they are working to a univerſall Licentiouſneſſe, as well in the Civil State, as in matters of Religion; by which liberty, all truth, and every mans property, with the Government which is the band of humane ſociety, will be deſtroyed. I had thought to have cloſed here, but <hi>I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conclude without a word upon that particular propoſed, that no Tythes be paid; becauſe I believe that taking away the Miniſters of the Goſpel with their maintenance, lies at the bottome of it: I ſay ſo upon this ground. Becauſe I did yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeak with any man who was for the taking away Tythes from Miniſters, without as good maintenance firſt provided in a ſetled and certain way, (which I could never yet hear pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded) but he was for the taking away the Miniſters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeves;</hi> and therefore they will not allow that the Miniſter is an office ordained by God (although nothing be more clear in his Word) but call them State Miniſters, or (as this Paper) pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſters, as though they were onely by ſome politique or civil conſtitution, and might be taken away at pleaſure: then which, nothing can be more contrary to the truth, neither is it onely cleare, that there are thoſe in the Church of Chriſt, whoſe office it is to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that by an Ordinance of Chriſt, <hi>They that preach the Gospel ſhould live of the Gospel. And however it be of a Divine Right, that Minſters ſhould have a maintenance, yet the proportion, diſtribution, uſe, and enjoyment of it is from, and by a civill right, whereupon they hold and poſſeſſe their Tythes by the Laws of the Kingdom; and have as legall a Freehold in their Tythes, as any man hath to his Land.</hi> And the Law doth provide full as good a remedy to the Miniſter for recovering his right of the Tythes, as to any Impropriator, or other man in the Kingdom, for any thing he enjoyes. <hi>But the Paper ſaith, it is a grievance and oppreſſion.</hi> I believe it is a grievance to thoſe men that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters live, or have any thing; But how comes it to be an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion? Is it oppreſſion to pay to others what is legally due to them? Theſe men may conſider, that if Tythes be taken from the Miniſters, or Impropriators, yet there is neither right nor Juſtice, that they by whom they are payable ſhould have them<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43435:8"/>to their own uſe, for they have nothing that might make or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive a right or title to them. They never payed any Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for them, they did not purchaſe, nor were they conveighed to them: when their Land was bought, it was under this charge, that Tythes ſhould be payed out of it. In a word, there may as much be ſaid in juſtice reaſon, or equity, why they ſhould not pay any quit Rents, Rent Charges, Annuities, or other charges that lies upon their land, as why they ſhould not pay Tythes: And <hi>do but give them Tythes upon their crying out that it is a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and oppreſſion, and they will in a ſhort time (I am confident) upon the ſame grounds, cry out upon all other payments and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges out of their Land; and it is like the Rent to the Landlord will not be payed long after, for they will be all alike a grievance and oppreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do obſerve that there are two notable pieces of juſtice in the conſequence of this particular of theirs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the Impropriator ſhall be ſatisfied (yet I know not how, where, or by whom) before his Tythes be taken away. Yet the poor Miniſter that holds his by as good Law and right ſhall have his firſt taken from him, and play an after-game for his maintenance which might gain their point; when by that means they might be driven from their Churches to go abroad to beg, becauſe they cannot work.</p>
            <p>And the other is, that they would have this new Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to take Tythes from the Miniſters, to whom they belong in juſtice and right, and to give them unto other people who have no right at all to them. And when they have got the Miniſters Tythes, then they propoſe that they may have maintenance. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided alwaies, that (it being againſt their Conſcience) they may pay them nothing. Nor others pay any thing, all payments being oppreſſive, and they are to have nothing but in an unoppreſſive way. By all which appears, that they intend to take away the Miniſters, and get their means to themſelves for their paines. I do not in this plead my own caſe, for I do and ſhall willingly pay Tythes but I receive none.</p>
            <p>I have thus lookt into theſe <hi>Foundations of Freedome,</hi> and told you in part what I have ſeen, wherein I <hi>muſt leave every
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43435:9"/>Reader to his own judgement: I ſhall only upon the whole matter give you mine. That under the colour of laying new foundations, all the old Foundations of Religion, Parliaments, Laws, Liberties, and Property: are ſtrongly endeavoured to be undermined, pluckt up and deſtroyed.</hi> And all the materials I find brought to this new building are ſuch (in my judgement) as onely tend to Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; <hi>therefore it ſhall be againſt my will if I live in it, or neer it, becauſe it hath no ground work. For here is a Government without Authority,</hi> A Magiſtrate without power; If a Miniſter, yet without maintenance. <hi>A People left to be of any Religion, or of all Religions, or of no Religion as they pleaſe.</hi> It is therefore (in my judgement) altogether unſutable to any who deſire to live ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I would not be ſo angry with thoſe that ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it, as to reſolve preſently to fall out with them. I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that it hath ſtill been our enemies work to divide us, <hi>England</hi> from
<hi>Scotland,</hi> and one from another: Let it ſtill be our work to unite, and not be ſo wicked and unwiſe, as to ruine a righteous cauſe, and our ſelves with it. But <hi>let us lay aſide this Paper, and all dividing and party Projects, and make it our ſtudy how to ſatisfie and ſecure one another, that we may live in love and peace; Which as it hath ever been my hearty deſire, ſo it ſhall ever be my faithful endeavour, and moſt earneſt prayer to that God, who out of all theſe ſhakings is only able to bring a good ſettlement to this poor diſtracted Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43435:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
